<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Douglas Vaghetti</title>
    <link>https://vaghetti.dev/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Douglas Vaghetti</description>
    <image>
      <url>https://vaghetti.dev/apple-touch-icon.png</url>
      <link>https://vaghetti.dev/apple-touch-icon.png</link>
    </image>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2022 13:29:43 -0300</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://vaghetti.dev/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Tibia was wild in mostly bad ways. I really miss it.</title>
      <link>https://vaghetti.dev/posts/tibia/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2022 13:29:43 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vaghetti.dev/posts/tibia/</guid>
      <description>Tibia is a 2D MMORPG released in 1997. It is one of the oldest MMOs still active. You can see their official screenshots page to get a sense of what it looks like. Tibia&amp;rsquo;s graphics improved since the game was released, but not much.
Although the game was pretty solid technologically when it was released, it was quickly surpassed graphically in the following years. Even with dated graphics, Tibia&amp;rsquo;s popularity peaked in 2007.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Tibia is a 2D MMORPG released in 1997. It is one of the oldest MMOs still active. You can see their <a href="https://www.tibia.com/abouttibia/?subtopic=screenshots">official screenshots</a> page to get a sense of what it looks like. Tibia&rsquo;s graphics improved since the game was released, but not much.</p>
<p>Although the game was pretty solid technologically when it was released, it was quickly surpassed graphically in the following years. Even with dated graphics, Tibia&rsquo;s popularity peaked in 2007. For comparison, this is what World of Warcraft <a href="https://www.gamingcfg.com/screenshot/World-of-Warcraft-2007-8264">looked like in 2007</a>. So what was going on in 2007?</p>
<p>Trough a mixture of cultural and technological reasons, Tibia was the only viable MMO option for lots of people in Brazil back then. By 2007, any PC could run it. It didn&rsquo;t require a very good internet connection and, most importantly, it 100% free to play. Check out their <a href="https://www.tibia.com/community/?subtopic=worlds">servers list</a>, almost half of the servers are in South America. I was one of these people in Brazil. Being their only option might get people to give the game a chance, but what was it that made them stay?</p>
<h2 id="asking-players-to-do-boring-things-was-ok">Asking players to do boring things was ok</h2>
<p>I&rsquo;m not talking about grinding here. Tibia has plenty of that too. I&rsquo;m talking about spending hours and hours hitting self-cloning slimes with weak weapons to improve your fighting ability. When you made it to higher levels, it could take hours to go up a single skill point, and this skill point would not even make much of a difference in the damage you dealt. We called it <em>training</em>.</p>
<p>Mages were not exempt either, for a long time, Druids in Tibia would spend hours waiting for their mana to recharge to cast a cure spell in a rune so it could be used later in combat at no mana cost. That was it, really. You were supposed to just stand there and wait for your mana to recharge, only to create a rune and do the same thing over and over again.</p>
<h2 id="frustrating-players-was-ok-too">Frustrating players was OK too</h2>
<p>Tibia could also be incredibly punishing. Back then, when you died, you would lose 10% of your character&rsquo;s total experience. In earlier levels, that would mean you lost one level, sometimes not even a whole level. But in higher levels, you&rsquo;d lose multiple levels that took days or even months to recover.</p>
<p>Death could happen anytime. Even if you were just hunting weak monsters or simply travelling from one place to another, players could attack you. There were no level restrictions. Anyone could kill you almost anywhere, anytime.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup></p>
<p>For example, it was standard practice to kill players who didn&rsquo;t seem to be looking at their screen, and thus just idle. The game actively rewarded you for it. When you killed another player, you could take all the items they were carrying and, with some luck, even some equipment they had on. I still have not-fond-at-all memories of throwing my items in the water to destroy them just so my assassin wouldn&rsquo;t have them out of sheer spite.</p>
<p>Check <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=30324846">this</a> hacker news thread for some more old school Tibia reminiscing.</p>
<h2 id="the-ability-to-inflict-psychological-pain">The ability to inflict (psychological) pain</h2>
<p>With PVP anywhere and great punishment for death, higher level players and guilds could cause real pain to each other. That is <strong><em>power</em></strong> in its most raw shape! Strong guilds could rule their worlds through fear!</p>
<p>Things could get wild in bigger servers. Powerful guilds would hunt players: Any member of the guild would kill the hunted player on sight or call for reinforcements. Sometimes guilds would have players guarding over the most sought after dungeons and demand money to use them. Yes, those were virtual gangs, with extortion, infighting, gang wars and all.</p>
<h2 id="why-we-cant-have-old-tibia-anymore">Why we can&rsquo;t have old Tibia anymore</h2>
<p>Times are different now. Players are not willing to deal with frustration like they were back then. Much of what made Tibia special were things that are generally regarded as bad game design nowadays.</p>
<p>The game rewarded you for doing repetitive things with no real challenge. Players were punished to extreme extents due to completely silly things like being AFK or just being in the wrong place at the wrong time. Some high level player could simply decide they didn&rsquo;t like your clothes and <a href="https://tibia.fandom.com/wiki/Rooking">rook you</a>. If there&rsquo;s a word for it, there is a story behind it.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m not saying these changes are bad. If I was to start playing Tibia today without being influenced by nostalgia, I&rsquo;m sure I would quickly drop it without thinking much of it.</p>
<p>Nonetheless, these game design decisions created a really unique virtual world that provided very meaningful experiences to a lot of people, like me. And I just can&rsquo;t shake off the feeling our lives are a tiny bit worse because that world is gone and it seems like it can&rsquo;t be created again.</p>
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>This was only the case in PVP servers, players also had the choice of playing in non-PVP worlds if they chose to.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Developer tooling must spark joy</title>
      <link>https://vaghetti.dev/posts/joy/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Feb 2022 15:46:03 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vaghetti.dev/posts/joy/</guid>
      <description>Way too often, I see tech companies provide their developers with tooling that can get their job done but doesn&amp;rsquo;t spark joy. I believe that&amp;rsquo;s a big mistake. Developers expect joy from their tools, and they will go to great lengths to get them, either in their current job or elsewhere.
Which tools spark joy? I&amp;rsquo;m not going to get into the topic of which tools spark joy and which don&amp;rsquo;t.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Way too often, I see tech companies provide their developers with tooling that can get their job done but doesn&rsquo;t spark <em>joy</em>. I believe that&rsquo;s a big mistake. Developers expect joy from their tools, and they will go to great lengths to get them, either in their current job or elsewhere.</p>
<h2 id="which-tools-spark-joy">Which tools spark joy?</h2>
<p>I&rsquo;m not going to get into the topic of which tools spark joy and which don&rsquo;t. For some people, anything other than a Mac won&rsquo;t do. For others, a desktop running Linux with loads of RAM will be the best option. Some people like noisy mechanical keyboards, others, 4k monitors. There are even people who <em>enjoy</em> working on windows.</p>
<p>I get it. These things I&rsquo;m talking about can be expensive. Not all companies can afford them. I live in Brazil, <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2021/10/19/brazil-has-the-most-expensive-new-macbook-pro-and-airpods-3-in-the-world">computers are very expensive here</a>.</p>
<p>Nonetheless, I see companies that could definitely afford better gear, but hold back on providing it because it doesn&rsquo;t seem rational. I&rsquo;ll give some examples of this happening and go trough why it is a bad decision on the long run.</p>
<h2 id="developing-country-tech-company-starter-pack">Developing country tech company starter pack</h2>
<p>I visit linkedin every so often. Every single time I go there, I&rsquo;ll see someone in my direct or indirect contacts switching jobs and posting a picture of their new work equipment. It almost always looks like this:</p>
<ul>
<li>Some company branded swag: t-shirts, paper notebooks, a coffee mug, the list goes on.</li>
<li>A Dell notebook. Not one of their good ones, but one that can get the job done. Usually with something like a latest gen i5 processor and 16 gbs of ram</li>
<li>A mouse, because the trackpad is awful.</li>
<li>A monitor, usually full hd, but never bigger than 23&quot;.</li>
<li>A generic membrane keyboard.</li>
</ul>
<p>There&rsquo;s nothing inherently wrong here, even with top of the line computers, with a nice trackpad and a 4k screen, most people would still want a separate monitor, a keyboard and a mouse.</p>
<p>What is bad about this setup is that it doesn&rsquo;t spark joy. Developers will try to find ways to get it.</p>
<h2 id="people-will-seek-joy-one-way-or-another">People will seek joy, one way or another</h2>
<p>A friend of mine used to work at a small company. They would also provide their employes with the standard low end Dell + peripherals kit that is uninspiring but gets the job done. What was interesting about this company was it didn&rsquo;t really force employees to work with hardware they provided. Senior leadership would just bring their personal Macbooks to the office, and slowly the developers working from home started buying more powerful desktops with their personal money and working with them.</p>
<p>Everyone who could afford it was avoiding the hardware the company provided! It was completely demoralizing! I wasn&rsquo;t because of hardware alone, but my friend left the company shortly after and they have serious retention problems to this day.</p>
<p>This isn&rsquo;t limited to small companies either. I heard of similar stories in fortune 500 companies in the tech sector. They had stricter controls in place to ensure employees would use the company provided joyless hardware. What ended up happening was politicking. People would make all sorts of excuses to justify why their projects needed macs. Many would complain peers in other countries got better gear working on the exact same project. Some also bought peripherals with their own money, such as noise-canceling headphones and better keyboards.</p>
<p>In this case, the leadership team was smarter about it and just upgraded everyone&rsquo;s hardware.</p>
<h2 id="yet-it-can-be-hard-to-argue-in-favor-of-joy">Yet, it can be hard to argue in favor of joy</h2>
<p>Joy clearly matters. People will waste lots of time and even spend their own money to get it, dragging morale down. A lack of joy might be the straw that breaks the camel&rsquo;s back and leads someone to start looking for new opportunities.</p>
<p>Still, it can be incredibly hard to convince a manager to just pay for better hardware. A manager is part of a chain of people that ultimately need to justify their costs in terms of productivity. It is pretty hard to justify additional hardware costs based on this vague notion of joy.</p>
<p>At the end of the day, a mechanical keyboard or a 4k monitor won&rsquo;t directly allow anyone to deliver features faster. But they will make people happier. Happier people tend to be more pleasant to work with and to stay longer at their jobs. Which in the end, does have an impact on productivity.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Building meaningful relationships with remote colleagues</title>
      <link>https://vaghetti.dev/posts/remote/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Feb 2022 20:23:11 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vaghetti.dev/posts/remote/</guid>
      <description>I have a diary. I&amp;rsquo;ve been writing on it somewhat regularly since 2014. I find it extremely useful and I think everyone should at least give it a try. I do it for two reasons:
When writing, a diary is a great tool for organizing thoughts and making decisions. The process of writing forces you to articulate thoughts with much greater clarity than you could by just sitting down and thinking.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I have a diary. I&rsquo;ve been writing on it somewhat regularly since 2014. I find it extremely useful and I think everyone should at least give it a try. I do it for two reasons:</p>
<p>When writing, a diary is a great tool for organizing thoughts and making decisions. The process of writing forces you to articulate thoughts with much greater clarity than you could by just sitting down and thinking.</p>
<p>The other benefit of having a diary is being able to read it after some time. Our brains have a tendency of distorting our memories in some really nasty ways. A diary is like a brain-tampering-proof series of snapshots of our past thoughts and feelings.</p>
<p>Some weeks ago, I  decided to read some old diary entries. I was specially interested in the period where the pandemic was starting and I began working remotely. I had this feeling on the back of my head for a while that I wasn&rsquo;t evolving professionally as fast now as I was before the pandemic.</p>
<p>As I read my past entries in the diary, it became clear that it was just my brain painting an overly rosy picture of the past. Back in 2020, right before the pandemic started, my past self was already complaining about this very same feeling! It had nothing to do with remote work, it was just my unreasonable expectations once again.</p>
<p>In the process of reading these diary entries, however, something else became very clear: In office work was making me a better person in ways that were not even related to work.</p>
<h2 id="you-are-kind-of-the-average-of-the-people-you-spend-most-time-with">You are (kind of) the average of the people you spend most time with</h2>
<p>As I read these past entries, I began to realize how much I changed due to the influence of work colleagues.</p>
<p>From things like investments and career management, all the way to politics and the ethics of eating meat, work colleagues exposed me to new ways of thinking. In many cases, I did not agree with their opinions, but they broadened my views in very useful ways nonetheless.</p>
<p>After reading all the entries until remote work started, it became clear to me that these people were really making me smarter by osmosis. <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup></p>
<h2 id="is-this-really-the-role-of-work-colleagues">Is this really the role of work colleagues?</h2>
<p>There&rsquo;s a perfectly reasonable argument to be made that exposing you to new ways of thinking about factory farming or the Boggleheads subreddit is not really the role of work colleagues. I am sure some people will read all of this and say <em>&ldquo;Just get some friends!&rdquo;</em>.</p>
<p>I mostly agree. Work should be about work, and if that&rsquo;s all people want from work, they should definitely be able to get just that, without any sort of negative repercussion.</p>
<p>But these lost relationships were valuable to me, and I&rsquo;m sure they were valuable to other people too. They&rsquo;re mostly gone with remote work.</p>
<h2 id="building-meaningful-remote-relationships">Building meaningful remote relationships</h2>
<p>I&rsquo;m not arguing against remote work. I love remote work. I don&rsquo;t intend on going back to in-office work as long as I reasonably can. But I think we need to figure out ways to allow these relationships to flourish for remote work to really succeed for most people on the long run.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve had many meaningful conversations that truly expanded my views over pure text alone. So I don&rsquo;t think it really is a technical limitation. These are just not the kinds of conversations we&rsquo;re having with our remote work colleagues. I feel like we just need to figure out the right culture and processes to allow them to happen. And again, if people don&rsquo;t want to be part of them, that&rsquo;s absolutely fine.</p>
<p>So how can we have these conversations on a remote setting? I don&rsquo;t really have an answer, but I can offer some food for thought.</p>
<h2 id="so-how-does-the-solution-look-like">So how does the solution look like?</h2>
<p>I see some colleagues just chatting about non-work stuff in scheduled meetings after the meeting discussions are finished, and I think that&rsquo;s a good start, but far from a real solution. I also notice some teams have open video chat rooms that people can join at any point to talk about anything, like a virtual watercooler. Again, they don&rsquo;t seem to have much adoption.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m a bit skeptical about a &ldquo;cultural solution&rdquo;, something that is officially integrated into company processes. You can&rsquo;t just build meaningful relationships by having some scheduled meetings or doing some exercises proposed by someone from HR with your work colleagues. I feel like the solution will come from outside.</p>
<p>Heck, we as a society figured out <em>dating</em> on the internet. Some people have entire romantic relationships with people they&rsquo;ve only known virtually and they&rsquo;re happy. I&rsquo;m sure we can figure out meaningful relationships with work colleagues.</p>
<p>Maybe it will take shape as a Slack alter-ego? A group chat app that is invitation-only. There would be no single official company profile, just some profiles created by employees where they can invite one another. Maybe some smaller private chat rooms? A central place where you can send internal tweets to everyone in the company? Messages that disappear over time? Optional anonymity? Am I just describing Discord? The solution space is quite big.</p>
<p>Chances are, we won&rsquo;t figure this out on the first try. The first dating services looked a lot like facebook, in the end it turned out it was much better to just brute-force it and show people hundreds of pictures of strangers and ask if they look interesting.</p>
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
<p>By the same logic, I was making them <em>dumber</em>. I would rather think it wasn&rsquo;t <em>quite</em> like osmosis.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wordle is pretty damn smart in many subtle ways</title>
      <link>https://vaghetti.dev/posts/wordle/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Feb 2022 18:03:17 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vaghetti.dev/posts/wordle/</guid>
      <description>I love Wordle. I play it pretty much every single day. I also play the portuguese version immediately afterwards too. It is now part of my morning routine.
Wordle is one of those ideas that just click and immediately have you wishing you were the one to have them. If you don&amp;rsquo;t know what Wordle is, just click here and play it. Give it a try, you&amp;rsquo;ll probably like it. It won&amp;rsquo;t take you more than 10 minutes.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I love <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/games/wordle/">Wordle</a>. I play it pretty much every single day.
I also play the <a href="https://term.ooo">portuguese version</a> immediately afterwards too.
It is now part of my morning routine.</p>
<p>Wordle is one of those ideas that just click and immediately have you wishing you were the one to have them.
If you don&rsquo;t know what Wordle is, just click <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/games/wordle/">here</a> and play it.
Give it a try, you&rsquo;ll probably like it. It won&rsquo;t take you more than 10 minutes.</p>
<p>On a superficial level, there&rsquo;s nothing special about Wordle, every day, everyone gets a 5 character word, you have to guess what it is.
As you try, you get some information about what you got wrong that helps you move towards the correct answer. You only get 6 attempts.</p>
<p>It is a very simple core mechanic, any programmer with some frontend knowledge could put together something similar in a few hours.</p>
<p>What makes Wordle special is not the core mechanic itself, but the series of very intelligent decisions that were made around this very simple (but still fun) core mechanic.</p>
<h2 id="no-ads-no-log-in">No ads, no log-in</h2>
<p>When you first open the Wordle website, you&rsquo;re immediately greeted with a simple text tutorial explaining how to play the game.
There are no ads, no login prompt, no attempts to get you to buy skins or donate money.
Compare this with something like <a href="https://www.agar.io/">agar.io</a> or any other <code>.io</code> hyper casual game and you&rsquo;ll see Wordle is truly special in this regard.</p>
<p>I know, people need to make a living. Games are not hosted for free, specially when they&rsquo;re multiplayer games with loads of players.
Wordle was acquired by the New York Times some weeks ago, so I wouldn&rsquo;t expect it to stay this way for too long anyway.</p>
<p>No ads is just icing on the cake, not having them is more a privilege of a game that doesn&rsquo;t need to make money than a true long term differentiator. There are other design decisions that make Wordle truly shine.</p>
<h2 id="one-word-per-day">One word per day</h2>
<p>There&rsquo;s one new word every day. Everyone gets the same word.</p>
<p>You only get to play once, if you try 6 words and fail, Wordle will just give you the answer.
There&rsquo;s no point in opening another browser or cleaning your cache to keep trying.
No need for an account either.
Wordle will ensure you can only try once a day by spoiling you if you fail.
You can&rsquo;t tryhard your way into victory.</p>
<p>It is simple and elegant. Even when you lose, the game ends on a high note.</p>
<p>After you played the day&rsquo;s word, that&rsquo;s it. You want more but you&rsquo;ll have to come back on the next day.</p>
<p>Hoping users will remember your hyper casual game with an average play time of a couple minutes sounds like a sure way to be quickly forgotten, but wordle gets around this just as elegantly.</p>
<h2 id="sharing">Sharing</h2>
<p>After you finish a Wordle match, you get a share button. If you click it, you don&rsquo;t get a list of supported social media websites or some twitter OAuth prompt.
All you get is a message saying <em>&ldquo;Copied results to clipboard&rdquo;</em>. This is what mine for today&rsquo;s puzzle looks like:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-markdown" data-lang="markdown"><span style="display:flex;"><span>Wordle 248 4/6
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>⬜🟨⬜🟨⬜
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>🟨⬜⬜🟨⬜
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>🟨🟨🟨🟨🟨
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>🟩🟩🟩🟩🟩
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>This is, again, smart on multiple levels.</p>
<p>It communicates how your game went in meaningful detail without spoiling the day&rsquo;s word for people who haven&rsquo;t played it yet. At the same time, people who already played today can immediately look at it and know you were struggling in the same ways, which can be pretty fun and engaging.</p>
<p>It also brings players back into the game, but not in an annoying way like Farmville Facebook notifications. Shared Wordle games actively improve your experience by adding a social factor.</p>
<p>You can share it anywhere, it is just some emoji and text. There&rsquo;s not even an image or hyperlink. Anywhere you can type, you can share your Wordle game.</p>
<h2 id="and-repeat">And repeat</h2>
<ul>
<li>You play your first Wordle match, you have some fun, but it is short, you want some more but you have to wait, so you move on with your day and forget about it.</li>
<li>On the next day, you&rsquo;re scrolling Twitter and someone posts their Wordle score. You remember the game exists, you remember you wanted more. You play it again.</li>
<li>If you&rsquo;re so inclined, you share your score as well.</li>
<li>Repeat</li>
</ul>
<p>Do this for a couple of days, and you&rsquo;re hooked. You don&rsquo;t even need Twitter to remind you about Wordle anymore.
Some people in my feed play the new word every day after midnight.</p>
<h2 id="wordle-and-senior-engineers">Wordle and senior engineers</h2>
<p>Some people say the biggest difference between an engineer and a senior engineer is not on the code they write, but on the senior engineer ability to figure out ways to not write code.</p>
<p>Wordle is a great example of how this looks like in practice. It avoids loads of complexity at design time, making many features unnecessary and still delivering a superior experience in the end.</p>
<p>No login, just give users a satisfying end when they fail. No social media integration, some emojis they can paste anywhere clipboard will do. No ads, make something people like first, figure money out later. Add a tight social media reminders + leave users wanting more loop, and you have a hit.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Times are great for programmers now. How does it end?</title>
      <link>https://vaghetti.dev/posts/times-are-great/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Feb 2022 13:05:41 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vaghetti.dev/posts/times-are-great/</guid>
      <description>It is a good time to be in tech right now: soaring salaries, daily LinkedIn recruiter spam, people bootcamping their way into career switches to tech, remote work allowing you to work for a major tech company making triple digit salaries from the beach. It really feels like every single company is trying to recruit programmers nowadays, and doing whatever they can to get them.
I’m certainly happy with the current state of affairs, but I can’t help but wonder: How does it end?</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>It is a good time to be in tech right now: soaring salaries, daily LinkedIn recruiter spam, people bootcamping their way into career switches to tech, remote work allowing you to work for a major tech company making triple digit salaries from the beach. It really feels like every single company is trying to recruit programmers nowadays, and doing whatever they can to get them.</p>
<p>I’m certainly happy with the current state of affairs, but I can’t help but wonder: How does it end? Things are obviously good for us programmers and we would certainly like for them to stay this way.</p>
<p>Business owners, on the other hand, are not quite happy. You see, no sane CEO is going to issue a press release saying &ldquo;<em>yeah, business is booming, record profits something something, great opportunities for double digit growth in something something Asia, by the way I&rsquo;d be really happy if I could pay less money to my employees</em>&rdquo;. That&rsquo;s just not the kind of thing you <em>say</em>, but everyone <em>kinda knows</em> it is true. The CEO&rsquo;s job is to make as much profit as possible. Higher salaries mean less profit. It&rsquo;s just how the game works.</p>
<p>Salaries are a matter of supply and demand. Lots of companies trying to hire not-that-many programmers means salaries go up, if it was the other way around, they would go down. So how do the good times end? Either demand for tech workers goes down or supply goes up.</p>
<h2 id="supply-goes-up">Supply goes up</h2>
<p>The markets are doing their thing. Everyone sees tech workers making money and just generally having a good time and they think: &ldquo;Hey that sounds like a good career choice&rdquo;. Every year we get more Computer science graduates. Code bootcamps are also booming.</p>
<p>But these are long term changes that are barely making up for the also increasing demand, so I don&rsquo;t see any meaningful change coming from this front at last in the short to medium term.</p>
<h2 id="demand-goes-down">Demand goes down</h2>
<p>This is where I think the most interesting (and faster) changes could happen. Jeff Besos famously said <em>&ldquo;Your margin is my opportunity&rdquo;</em>. Tech worker wages are certainly a massive opportunity right now! There is a lot of money to be made by making products that allow businesses to get things done with less programmers, maybe no programmers at all.</p>
<p>I know it sounds kind of evil putting it like that, but bear with me.</p>
<h3 id="developer-tooling-improvements">Developer tooling improvements</h3>
<p>Developers are expensive. If a new IDE shows up and they can deliver stuff 5% faster, that means you can have 5% less programmers! Of course the IDE has a price, but it is almost certainly cheaper than 5% of a developer.</p>
<p>I haven&rsquo;t seen that much improvement in developer tooling over the last couple of years, but AI is making some really meaningful progress in this field with things like github <a href="https://copilot.github.com">copilot</a>. For now it only delivers some smarter auto complete suggestions, not that far in the future we could see AIs finding bugs in our code, or even generating tests.</p>
<h3 id="no-code--low-code">No code / Low code</h3>
<p>People have been trying this for decades and it never really worked out. I can&rsquo;t think of a single product that was able to get to any meaningful degree of success running on top of some low code platform.</p>
<p>But hey, deep learning was in a similar spot in the 90s and now we have real products that use it and it <em>mostly</em> works. The incentive has never been greater. The more expensive developers get, the more money there is to be made by making them less necessary.</p>
<h3 id="decreased-investment">Decreased investment</h3>
<p>I think this is the most likely scenario. Much of the demand for programmers right now stems more from expectations of future profits than from profits being currently made.</p>
<p>Many companies hiring now are unprofitable companies surviving on investor money with the expectation of future profit. If the economic conditions change and investors decide they don&rsquo;t like tech companies anymore, many of them will inevitably close. Less companies hiring also means less demand.</p>
<h1 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h1>
<p>This post might have sounded gloomish, at least for programmers, but honestly I don&rsquo;t think there&rsquo;s that much to worry about. Even if we enter some new dotcom bubble and a good chunk of our startup ecosystem dies off, demand for tech is spreading across all industries, businesses everywhere are digitizing their operations and these systems will need to be maintained somehow.</p>
<p>Also, salaries are notoriously <a href="https://www.investopedia.com/terms/s/sticky-wage-theory.asp">sticky</a>, so instead of a salary reduction we could see a workforce reduction instead. Maybe it is better to start replying to the linkedin recruiter spam just in case?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
